A Guide to the Evergreen and Woodland Cemeteries Records, 1893-2016
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Evergreen and Woodland Cemeteries Records, 1893-2016
The Library of Virginia
52003
14.5 cubic feet (49 boxes)
Evergreen and Woodland Cemeteries
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Enrichmond Foundation.
Historical Information
Evergreen Cemetery is a historic African-American cemetery located in the East End neighborhood of Richmond, Virginia. Founded in 1891 as an African-American equivalent to Hollywood Cemetery, many notable African Americans are interred at Evergreen, including Maggie L. Walker, John Mitchell, Jr., and A.D. Price. Located in Henrico County, Woodland Cemetery was established in 1917 by the Woodland Cemetery Corporation, led by president John Mitchell, Jr. The site of interment of Arthur Ashe, Woodland Cemetery is the home to many of Richmond's wealthy and noteworthy African-American residents. Both cemeteries were created before the establishment of a 1919 Richmond city ordinance that required cemeteries to have perpetual care funds in order to finance upkeep. As a result, both cemeteries fell into states of disrepair. Maintained for decades by their respective cemetery associations, Evergreen Cemetery was sold to Metropolitan Memorial Services, Incorporated in 1970. Metropolitan Memorial Services maintained control of Evergreen Cemetery until their bankruptcy in 1973. Following the bankruptcy, many former officers of the Metropolitan Memorial Services founded the U.K. Corporation, which purchased Evergreen and Woodland Cemeteries sometime in the 1970's. The Enrichmond Foundation acquired Evergreen Cemetery in May 2017; Woodland Cemetery is currently unowned.
Scope and Content
Records, 1893-2016, of the Evergreen and Woodland Cemeteries include interment cards records, financial records, and general files. Interment records are in the form of ledgers and index cards. Financial records relate to both Evergreen and Woodland Cemeteries and include general account ledgers, ledgers of funeral home accounts, annual care ledgers, employee records, contracts, and lot and stock certificates. The general files include applications for memorial foundations at both cemeteries, burial permits, and correspondence. Over time, the interment and financial records of Evergreen and Woodland have become intermingled. Collection also contains maps of Evergreen and Woodland Cemeteries and segments of a map, possibly of Oakwood Cemetery.
Contents List
- Interment Records, 1893-2016., Extent: 29 boxes. (Box 1-29)
  Interment records of Evergreen and Woodland Cemeteries include both index cards and ledgers. The interment ledgers include the earliest surviving records of both cemeteries, though there are significant gaps. The ledgers detail the name and age of deceased, place of death, date of burial, funeral director, lot and grave number, and the cost of burial. Ledger entries from 1929 to 1943 include the cause of death. The interment cards include the name, age, sex, color, and civil condition of deceased, place and date of death, date of burial, funeral home director, lot and grave number, cost of burial, and known lot owner. The 1893-1928 Evergreen Interment Ledger contains only entries of those interred whose surname begins with A-M. Some interment cards from the 1930's and 1940's also include cause of death. Index cards also detail burials which were later void or cancelled. Interment ledgers are arranged chronologically, while internment index cards are arranged alphabetically.
  Over time, some records of the Evergreen and Woodland Cemeteries have become intermingled. As a result, some Woodland interment index cards are filed within the Evergreen boxes, and vice versa.
  - Evergreen Interment Ledger, 1893-1928 (also available on Microfilm, Misc. Reel 6672). (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Evergreen Interment Ledger, 1926-1962 (also available on Microfilm, Misc. Reel 6672). (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Evergreen Interment Ledger, 1963-1969 (also available on Microfilm, Misc. Reel 6672). (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Woodland (corrected) Interment Cards, A-M, 1929-1949 (also available on Microfilm, Misc. Reel 1247). (Box 2)
  - Woodland (corrected) Interment Cards, N-Z, 1929-1949 (also available on Microfilm, Misc. Reels 1247 and 1248). (Box 3)
  - Evergreen Interment Cards, A-G, 1950-1969 (also available on Microfilm, Misc. Reels 1248 and 1249). (Box 4)
  - Evergreen Interment Cards, H-P, 1950-1969 (also available on Microfilm, Misc. Reels 1249 and 1250). (Box 5)
  - Evergreen Interment Cards, Q-Z, 1950-1969 (also available on Microfilm, Misc. Reels 1250 and 1251). (Box 6)
  - Evergreen Interment Cards, A-J, 1970-1993 (also available on Microfilm, Misc. Reels 1251 and 1252). (Box 7)
  - Evergreen Interment Cards, K-Z, 1970-1993 (also available on Microfilm, Misc. Reels 1252 and 1253). (Box 8)
  - Evergreen Interment Cards, A-Z, 1994-2000 (also available on Microfilm, Misc. Reels 6673 and 6674). (Box 9)
  - Evergreen Interment Cards, A-Z, 2001-2016 (also available on Microfilm, Misc. Reels 6675 and 6676). (Box 10)
  - Woodland Interment Ledger, 1929-1942. (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Woodland Interment Notebook, Lots B-F undated. (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Woodland Interment Notebook, Lots G-J, undated. (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Woodland Interment Notebook, Lots K-M, undated. (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Woodland Interment Notebook, Lots N-P, undated. (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Woodland Interment Notebook, Lots Q-S, undated. (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Woodland Interment Notebook, Lots T-Z, undated. (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Woodland Reserve Graves Ledger, 1970-1979. (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Woodland Interment Cards, A-Bozeman, 1920-1973 (also available on Misc. reels 1264-1265). (Box 12)
  - Woodland Interment Cards, Bracey-Certain, 1920-1973 (also available on Misc. reels 1265-1266). (Box 13)
  - Woodland Interment Cards, Chalmers-Duncan, 1920-1973 (also available on Misc. reels 1266-1267). (Box 14)
  - Woodland Interment Cards, Dungee-Gray, 1920-1973 (also available on Misc. reels 1267-1268). (Box 15)
  - Woodland Interment Cards, Green-I, 1920-1973 (also available on Misc. reels 1268-1269). (Box 16)
  - Woodland Interment Cards, J, 1920-1973 (also available on Misc. reels 1269-1270). (Box 17)
  - Woodland Interment Cards, K-Meyers, 1920-1973 (also available on Misc. reels 1270-1271). (Box 18)
  - Woodland Interment Cards, Mickens-Poytrass, 1920-1973 (also available on Misc. reels 1271-1272). (Box 19)
  - Woodland Interment Cards, Pratt-Scott, 1920-1973 (also available on Misc. reels 1272-1273). (Box 20)
  - Woodland Interment Cards, Settles-Teran, 1920-1973 (also available on Misc. reels 1273-1274). (Box 21)
  - Woodland Interment Cards, Thacker-Williams, 1920-1973 (also available on Misc. reels 1274-1276). (Box 22)
  - Woodland Interment Cards, Williams-Z, 1920-1973 (also available on Misc. reels 1276). (Box 23)
  - Woodland Interment Cards, A-G, 1973-1993 (also available on Misc. reels 1277-1278). (Box 24)
  - Woodland Interment Cards, H-Q, 1973-1993 (also available on Misc. reels 1278-1279). (Box 25)
  - Woodland Interment Cards, R-Z, 1973-1993 (also available on Misc. reels 1279-1280). (Box 26)
  - Woodland Interment Cards, A-Z, 1994-2015. (Box 27)
  - Void and cancelled interment cards, 1975-1993. (Box 28)
  - Interment Lot Ledger, 1924-1969 and undated,. (Box 29, Folder 1)
  - Interment Lot Ledger, A-D, 1929-1968. (Box 29, Folder 2)
  - Interment Lot Ledger, E-H, 1929-1968. (Box 29, Folder 3)
  - Interment Lot Ledger, M-S 1929-1968. (Box 29, Folder 4)
  - Interment Lot Ledger, 1954-1970. (Box 29, Folder 5)
  - Interment Lot Ledger, undated. (Box 29, Folder 6)
  - Interment Lot Ledger, undated. (Box 29, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous Interment Records, 1983, 2007, and undated. (Box 29, Folder 8)
- Business and Financial Records, 1903-2015., Extent: 18 boxes. (Box 30-47)
  Business and Financial Records include billing and payment index cards, account ledgers, check registers, reciept ledgers, annual card ledgers, lot contracts, funeral home account ledgers, stock and lot certificates, and miscellaneous receipts and financial notes. Many of the financial records do not clearly indicate which cemetery they relate to; records that do indicate this information include the cemetery name in the folder or box name. These records also include notable gaps and almost no records from the 1960's remain. Many of these records are damaged and have undergone conservation efforts. The original order of all ledgers is maintained and boxes 29 and 30 have been rearranged alphabetically. Over time, some records of the Evergreen and Woodland Cemeteries have become intermingled. As a result, some Woodland interment index cards are filed within the Evergreen boxes, and vice versa.
  - Evergreen and Woodland Billing Cards, 1952-1991. (Box 30)
  - Evergreen and Woodland Billing Cards, 1976-1979. (Box 31)
  - Woodland Lot Contracts, 1931-1942. (Box 32, Folder 1)
  - Woodland Lot Contracts, 1943. (Box 32, Folder 2)
  - Woodland Lot Contracts, 1944. (Box 32, Folder 3)
  - Woodland Lot Contracts, 1945. (Box 32, Folder 4)
  - Woodland Lot Contracts, 1946. (Box 32, Folder 5)
  - Woodland Lot Contracts, 1947. (Box 32, Folder 6)
  - Woodland Lot Contracts, 1948. (Box 32, Folder 7)
  - Woodland Interment Payments, 1954. (Box 32, Folder 8)
  - Woodland Interment Payments, 1954. (Box 32, Folder 9)
  - Woodland Interment Payments, 1954. (Box 32, Folder 10)
  - Woodland Interment Payments, 1954. (Box 32, Folder 11)
  - Woodland Interment Payments, 1954. (Box 32, Folder 12)
  - Woodland Interment Payments, 1954. (Box 32, Folder 13)
  - Account Ledger, 1929-1932. (Box 33, Folder 1)
  - Cash Journal and Account Ledger, 1941-1944. (Box 33, Folder 2)
  - Account Ledger, 1945-1948. (Box 33, Folder 3)
  - Account Ledger, 1948-1952. (Box 34, Folder 1)
  - Account Ledger, 1951-1957. (Box 34, Folder 2)
  - Account Ledger, 1952-1957. (Box 35, Folder 1)
  - Account Ledger, 1956-1961. (Box 35, Folder 2)
  - Alphabetical List of Names on Accounts, undated. (Box 36, Folder 1)
  - Accounts 1-16, 1929-1946. (Box 36, Folder 2)
  - Accounts 17-98, 1929-1930. (Box 36, Folder 3)
  - Accounts 99-167, 1930. (Box 36, Folder 4)
  - Accounts 168-251, 1930-1934. (Box 36, Folder 5)
  - Accounts 252-343, 1931-1949. (Box 36, Folder 6)
  - Accounts 344-427, 1932-1934. (Box 36, Folder 7)
  - Accounts 428-500, 1935-1941. (Box 36, Folder 8)
  - Accounts 501-597, 1935-1941. (Box 37, Folder 1)
  - Accounts 598-693, 1938-1940. (Box 37, Folder 2)
  - Accounts 694-797, 1941-1944. (Box 37, Folder 3)
  - Accounts 798-888, 1943-1945. (Box 37, Folder 4)
  - Accounts 895-1025, 1945-1947. (Box 37, Folder 5)
  - Account Ledger, 1983-1995. (Box 37, Folder 6)
  - Account Ledger, 1996-2001. (Box 37, Folder 7)
  - Account Ledger, 2002-2007. (Box 37, Folder 8)
  - Account Ledger, 2014-2015. (Box 37, Folder 9)
  - Account Ledger, undated. (Box 37, Folder 10)
  - Records of Employment and Earnings, 1974-1977. (Box 38, Folder 1)
  - Interment Billing and Payment Accounts, 1978-1979. (Box 38, Folder 2)
  - Cash and Check Register, 1974-1976. (Box 38, Folder 3)
  - Check Register, 1977-1978. (Box 38, Folder 4)
  - Check Register, 1977-1978. (Box 38, Folder 5)
  - Check Register, 1978. (Box 38, Folder 6)
  - Check Register, 1978-1979. (Box 38, Folder 7)
  - Check Register, 1978-1980. (Box 38, Folder 8)
  - Check Register, 1979-1980. (Box 38, Folder 9)
  - Check Register, 1980. (Box 38, Folder 10)
  - Check Register, 1981. (Box 38, Folder 11)
  - Check Register, 1981-1982. (Box 38, Folder 12)
  - Check Register, 1981-1982. (Box 38, Folder 13)
  - Check Register, 1981-1982. (Box 38, Folder 14)
  - Check Register, 1982. (Box 38, Folder 15)
  - Check Register, 1982-1983. (Box 38, Folder 16)
  - Check Register, 1982-1983. (Box 38, Folder 17)
  - Check Register, 1982-1983. (Box 38, Folder 18)
  - Check Register, 1983. (Box 38, Folder 19)
  - Check Register, 1983-1984. (Box 38, Folder 20)
  - Check Register, 1983-1984. (Box 38, Folder 21)
  - Check Register, 1984. (Box 38, Folder 22)
  - Check Register, 1984-1985. (Box 38, Folder 23)
  - Check Register, 1984-1986. (Box 39, Folder 1)
  - Check Register, 1985-1986. (Box 39, Folder 2)
  - Check Register, 1986-1987. (Box 39, Folder 3)
  - Check Register, 1986-1987. (Box 39, Folder 4)
  - Check Register, 1987-1988. (Box 39, Folder 5)
  - Check Register, 1988-1989. (Box 39, Folder 6)
  - Check Register, 1988-1989. (Box 39, Folder 7)
  - Check Register, 1988-1990. (Box 39, Folder 8)
  - Check Register, 1989-1990. (Box 39, Folder 9)
  - Check Register, 1989-1991. (Box 39, Folder 10)
  - Check Register, 1990. (Box 39, Folder 11)
  - Check Register, 1990-1991. (Box 39, Folder 12)
  - Check Register, 1992-1993. (Box 39, Folder 13)
  - Check Register, 1993-1994. (Box 39, Folder 14)
  - Check Register, 1994-1995. (Box 39, Folder 15)
  - Check Register, 1995-1996. (Box 39, Folder 16)
  - Check Register, 1996-1997. (Box 39, Folder 17)
  - Check Register, 1997-1998. (Box 39, Folder 18)
  - Check Register, 1998-1999. (Box 39, Folder 19)
  - Check Register, 1999-2002. (Box 40, Folder 1)
  - Check Register, 2000-2001. (Box 40, Folder 2)
  - Check Register, 2001-2002. (Box 40, Folder 3)
  - Check Register, 2002-2003. (Box 40, Folder 4)
  - Check Register, 2003. (Box 40, Folder 5)
  - Check Register, 2003. (Box 40, Folder 6)
  - Check Register, 2003-2004. (Box 40, Folder 7)
  - Check Register, 2001. (Box 41, Folder 1)
  - Check Register, 2004-2005. (Box 41, Folder 2)
  - Check Register, 2005. (Box 41, Folder 3)
  - Check Register, 2005. (Box 41, Folder 4)
  - Check Register, 2006. (Box 41, Folder 5)
  - Check Register, 2006. (Box 41, Folder 6)
  - Check Register, 2006-2007. (Box 42, Folder 1)
  - Check Register, 2007. (Box 42, Folder 2)
  - Check Register, 2007. (Box 42, Folder 3)
  - Check Register, 2007. (Box 42, Folder 4)
  - Check Register, 2007-2008. (Box 42, Folder 5)
  - Check Register, 2008. (Box 42, Folder 6)
  - Check Register, 2008. (Box 42, Folder 7)
  - Check Register, 2008-2009. (Box 43, Folder 1)
  - Check Register, 2009. (Box 43, Folder 2)
  - Check Register, 2009-2010. (Box 43, Folder 3)
  - Check Register, 2010. (Box 43, Folder 4)
  - Check Register, 2010. (Box 43, Folder 5)
  - Check Register, 2010-2011. (Box 43, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous Check Registers, 1991-1998 and undated. (Box 43, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous Financial Records, 1995-2004 and undated. (Box 43, Folder 8)
  - Lot Certificate Ledger, 1954-1958. (Box 44, Folder 1)
  - Receipt Ledger, 1978-1980. (Box 44, Folder 2)
  - Receipt Ledger, 1980-1985. (Box 44, Folder 3)
  - Receipt Ledger, 1985-1988. (Box 44, Folder 4)
  - Annual Care Ledger, A-B, 1931-1954. (Box 45, Folder 1)
  - Annual Care Ledger, C-D, 1946-1958. (Box 45, Folder 2)
  - Annual Care Ledger, E-H, 1941-1959. (Box 45, Folder 3)
  - Annual Care Ledger, J-K, 1945-1957. (Box 45, Folder 4)
  - Annual Care Ledger, L-P, 1946-1958. (Box 45, Folder 5)
  - Annual Care Ledger, R-S, 1933-1958. (Box 45, Folder 6)
  - Annual Care Ledger, T-W, 1941-1952. (Box 45, Folder 7)
  - Possibly Active Annual Care, 1993-2013. (Box 45, Folder 8)
  - Inactive Annual Care, 1993-2010. (Box 45, Folder 9)
  - Inactive Annual Care, 1993-2013. (Box 45, Folder 10)
  - Inactive Annual Care, undated. (Box 45, Folder 11)
  - Annual Care Ledger, A-D, 1978-2014. (Box 46, Folder 1)
  - Annual Care Ledger, E-L, 1978-2014. (Box 46, Folder 2)
  - Annual Care Ledger, M-R, 1978-2014. (Box 46, Folder 3)
  - Annual Care Ledger, S-Z 1978-2014. (Box 46, Folder 4)
  - Annual Care, A-D, 1978-2012. (Box 46, Folder 5)
  - Annual Care, E-L, 1991-2014. (Box 46, Folder 6)
  - Annual Care, M-Z, 1996-2014. (Box 46, Folder 7)
  - Lot Certificates, 1903-2009. (Box 47, Folder 1)
  - Funeral Home Account Ledger, 1930-1947. (Box 47, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous Receipts and Invoices, 1939-2013. (Box 47, Folder 3)
  - Funeral Home Account Ledger, 1947-1958. (Box 47, Folder 4)
  - Stock Certificates, 1973-1975. (Box 47, Folder 5)
  - U.K. Corporation Profits and Losses, 2002-2003. (Box 47, Folder 6)
  - Memorial Foundation Payment Receipts, 2004-2008. (Box 47, Folder 7)
  - Quarterly Reports, 2005-2006. (Box 47, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous Financial Notes, undated. (Box 47, Folder 9)
- General Files, 1929-2014., Extent: 2 boxes and 1 oversize folder. (Box 48-49)
  General Files include applications for Memorial Foundations, burial permits, correspondence, and maps. Correspondence from city government agencies, genealogists, legal counsel, family members of interred, and AmeriCorps is included. Also includes one folder of miscellaneous and undated notes. The applications for memorial foundations are arranged alphabetically.
  - AmeriCorps, 1999-2000. (Box 48, Folder 1)
  - Applications for Memorial Foundations, A-E, 2005-2010. (Box 48, Folder 2)
  - Applications for Memorial Foundations, F-L, 2004-2010. (Box 48, Folder 3)
  - Applications for Memorial Foundations, M-R, 2002-2010. (Box 48, Folder 4)
  - Applications for Memorial Foundations, S-Z, 2002-2010. (Box 48, Folder 5)
  - Burial Permits, 1929-2014. (Box 48, Folder 6)
  - Price Lists, 1971 and undated. (Box 48, Folder 7)
  - Maps, undated. (Box 48, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1930-1995. (Box 49, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1997-2006. (Box 49, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 2007-2016. (Box 49, Folder 3)
  - U.K. Corporation Memorandum, 1996-2006 and undated. (Box 49, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper Clippings and Press Releases, 1976-2009. (Box 49, Folder 5)
  - Department of Motor Vehicles, 1973-2013. (Box 49, Folder 6)
  - Freddie Fields Painting Services, undated. (Box 49, Folder 7)
  - Virginia Roots, 2002. (Box 49, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, undated. (Box 49, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, undated. (Box 49, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous Papers, undated. (Box 49, Folder 11)
  - Photographs of Unidentified People, undated. (Box 49, Folder 11)
  - Maps of Evergreen and Woodland Cemeteries, segments of possibly Oakwood Cemetery, undated. (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - Maps of Evergreen and Woodland Cemeteries, segments of possibly Oakwood Cemetery, undated. (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - Maps of Evergreen and Woodland Cemeteries undated. (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - Map of Evergreen Cemetery undated. (Box 22, Folder 5)